We're talking about the theory of debt and interest rates.
So, I want to talk
about a number of technical topics
first.
I'm going to start with
a model, an Irving Fisher model
of interest.
And then I'm going to talk about present values and
discount bonds, compound interest, conventional bonds,
the term structure of interest rates, and forward rates.
These are all technical things.
And then I want to get
back and think about what really
goes on in debt markets.
There's two assignments for this lecture.
One is several chapters out of the Fabozzi et al.
manuscript.
And then there's a chapter from my forthcoming book that
I'm currently writing.
But that is the most important.
It's the most meager chapter that I've given you yet.
So, the book is not done.
And so, I think the
real reference for this is the
Fabozzi manuscript at this point.
And then Oliver will give a
TA section that will clarify, I
think, some of the points.
So, anyway, what we're talking
about today is interest rates.
Interest rates.
So, the percent that you earn on
a loan or that you pay on a
loan, depending on what side of it you are.
And interest rates go back thousands of years.
It's an old idea.
Typically, it's a few percent a year, right?
The first question we want to
try to think about is, what
explains that?
Why is it a few percent a year?
And why not something completely different?
And why is it even a positive number?
Ever think of negative interest rates?
Well, these are basic questions.
So, I wanted to start with the history of thought.
And an economist from the 19th century,
Eugen von Boehm,
who wrote a book on the
theory of interest in the late 19th
century.
Actually, it was 1884.
And he has a long, very
verbose account of what causes interest
rates.
But basically, he came up with three explanations.
Why is the interest rate so high?
Well, the interest rate is something
like 5%, or 3%, or 7%,
or something in that range.
And he said there's really three causes.
One of them is technical progress.
That as the economy gets
more and more scientific information
about how to do things, things get more productive.
So, maybe the 3% or the 5%,
whatever it is, is the rate of
technical progress.
And that's how fast technology is improving.
But that's not the only
cause that von Boehm talked about.
Another one was advantages to roundaboutness.
That must be some translation from his German.
But the idea is that more roundabout production is more
productive.
This isn't technical progress.
It's more about the time.
And if someone can ask
you to make something directly right
now, you've got to use
the simplest and the most direct
way to do it, if you're
going to do it right now.
But if you have time, you
can do a more roundabout way.
You can make tools first and
do something else that makes you a
more efficient producer of this.
And so, maybe the interest rate
is a measure of the advantages
to roundaboutness.
And the other thing that Mark gave is time preference.
That people just prefer the present over the future.
They're impatient.
This is behavioral economics, I suppose.
This is psychology.
That, you know, you've got a
box of candy sitting there, and
you're looking at it, and
you're saying, well, I should really
enjoy that next year.
Maybe it would spoil by next year, next month.
But somehow you don't.
You have an impulse to consume now.
And the interest rate is the rate of time preference.
That maybe people are, you
know, why is the interest rate
It's because people are 5% happier to get something now
than to get it in the future.
So, he left that train of thought for us.
This was not mathematical economics.
It was literary economics.
But the next person I want to
mention in the history of thought is Irving Fisher, who
was a professor at Yale University.
But he wrote a book
in 1930 called Theory of Interest.
And it is the all-time classic.
I think, on this topic.
So, Irving Fisher is, he's talked about in your textbook
by Fibozzi, and talked about in many textbooks.
He graduated from Yale.
I mentioned this, since you're Yale undergrads.
He was a Yale undergrad.
Graduated, maybe it was in 1885.
And he got the first economics
PhD at Yale University in the
1890s.
And he just stayed here
in New Haven all his life.
And if you were living in
New Haven in the early 20th century,
you'd know him, because he was a jogger.
Nobody else jogged.
He would exercise and run around
campus, so everyone would see him.
In the 19-teens or 20s, nobody did that.
But he did.
He was a health nut, among other things.
And he was a great guy.
But I'm not going to talk,
I could talk a lot about him.
He's a fascinating guy.
I'll tell you one more story about him.
He would invite students to his house for dinner.
And he would explain to
them before dinner, that he believed
that proper eating required that
you chew every bite a hundred
times before you swallow it.
So, he would tell the students to do that.
And it slowed down conversation at dinner a great deal.
And he would tell them, that's
what he's known for, among other things,
his theory of interest.
So, this is what's talked about in your textbook.
And I wanted to start out
with Irving Fisher, because, by the way,
I don't know when this room was built.
Does anyone know?
Since he died in 47, he
probably lectured from the same blackboard, right?
So, I don't know, the same slate.
It could be, right?
It could go back to that time.
But I don't know.
But he would put back on the board
what he had on this board, I'm assuming,
sometime in the 1930s.
So, well, what your author,
your textbook author, Fibozzi, emphasizes
for a theory of interest is something
that came from Fisher, but it's very simple.
And he says, the interest rate, and
this is Fibozzi's distillation of Irving Fisher,
he says, the interest rate is the intersection
of a supply and demand curve for savings.
So, I'm going to put
saving, or S, on this axis.
And on this axis, I'm going to
put the interest rate, call that R.
I don't know why we commonly use R for interest.
It's not the first letter, it's
in the middle of the word.
And the interest rate is the supply of saving
at any time that people then wish to put in
the bank or someplace else to earn interest.
And the theory is that the higher
the interest rate, the more people will save.
So, we have an upward-sloping supply curve.
Now, this S means supply, whereas
this S down here means saving.
And then there's a demand for investment capital.
So, the more people put
in, the lower the interest rate.
So, this S gives out your saving to businesses.
And the businesses want to
know what the interest rate is.
The lower the interest rate, the more they'll demand.
So, we have a demand curve for saving.
And then the intersection of
the two is the interest rate.
Well, it gives the interest rate on this axis,
and the amount of saving on the other axis.
So, that's what Fabozzi covers in your text.
But I wanted to go back to another diagram
that Fabozzi et al. did not include in their textbook,
but it also comes from
the 1930 book, Theory of Interest.
And that is a diagram that shows a two-period story.
And the thing I like about this two-period diagram
is that it brings out the Boom-Valver causes
of interest rate in a very succinct way.
So, this is the second Irving Fisher diagram.
And I'm going to do a little storytelling about this.
You remember the book Robinson Crusoe?
It was written by Jonathan Swift in the 1700s.
It was the story of a man named Robinson Crusoe,
who was marooned on an island all by himself.
And he had to live
on his own with no help.
This is a famous story.
We call it a Robinson Crusoe economy.
There's only one person in the economy.
So, of course, there's no trade.
But we'll move to a little bit of trade.
I'm just telling you a
story of the rate of interest.
There will be a rate
of interest on Robinson Crusoe's island.
Okay?
So, here is...
I'm going to show here.
Consumption today.
And on this axis, consumption next year.
All right.
And I don't remember the novel.
Did anyone here read it?
You must have read.
Somebody must have read Robinson Crusoe.
But...
I'm not going to be true to the story.
The story I'm going to tell
is that Robinson Crusoe has some food.
That's all.
The whole economy just is...
Let's say it's grain.
I don't know how he got that on the island.
But he's got grain.
And he's deciding how much to eat this
year and how much to plant for next year.
So, the total amount of
grain he has is right here.
Okay?
So, that is his endowment of grain.
And he could eat.
That's the maximum he could eat.
But if he eats it all, there won't
be any grain to plant for next year.
Okay?
So, he'd better not eat it all.
Or he'll starve next year.
Now, in a simple linear production with technology
that's linear, he can choose to set aside
a certain amount of grain, which is the
difference between what he has and what he's consuming.
And then, that will produce grain next period.
So, I'm going to draw a straight line.
That's supposed to be a straight line.
These are all supposed to be straight lines here.
Okay?
Okay.
And that is his choice set under linear technology.
I'm drawing it with no decreasing returns.
The idea is that...
Okay?
So, for every bushel of grain that he
plants, he gets two bushels next year, or whatever
it is.
Okay?
And so, if he were to consume nothing this
period, he would have, if I drew this thing
with the right slope of minus
2, he would have twice as much.
This is the maximum he could have next period.
Okay?
And so, he could consume
anywhere along this point, this line.
Okay?
And this would be the simplest Robinson Crusoe economy.
Now, in fact, so what does he do?
Remember, from elementary micro theory,
he has indifference curves between consumption
today and consumption tomorrow.
Remember these?
These are like contours of his utility.
We typically draw them like this.
Okay?
So, what does he do?
He maximizes his utility and chooses a
point that with the highest indifference curve touching
the production possibility frontier.
This is the PPF, the production possibility frontier.
And that determines the amount that he
consumes and the amount that he saves.
So, he consumes this amount here.
And the difference between his endowment
and his consumption is his saving.
Okay?
So, he consumes this amount here.
And then, next period, he consumes this amount.
All right?
That's simple micro theory.
That's familiar to you.
Now, so, in this case, the interest rate,
the slope of this line, the slope is equal
to minus 1 plus r,
where r is the interest rate.
Okay?
So, in this case, I've told a very simple story.
It has only one interest rate.
It has only one Böhm-Bawerk cause.
It's roundaboutness.
Well, maybe there's technical progress, too.
I don't know.
It has maybe a couple of these causes.
If, as time goes by, Robinson Crusoe figures
out better how to grow grain, there could
be a technical progress component.
But preferences don't matter in this story, right?
The preferences are represented by his indifference curves.
And since I've got a linear production possibility
frontier, I can't just say, well, I'm going
to go with this.
I'm going to go with this.
And so, in this case, the indifference
curve, the indifference curve, is the possibility
frontier.
Impatience doesn't matter.
The interest rate, in this case, is decided
by the technology, the slope of the curve.
So, we don't have all of Böhm-Bawerk's causes yet.
Okay.
Next step.
That was the simplest Irving Fisher story.
The next step is, let's suppose, however,
that there are diminishing returns to investment
in the future.
So, let's say, we have a market share of grain.
All right.
That means, for example, maybe when he grows a
little bit of it, he's very good at it.
And he does produce a big crop.
But as he tries to grow
more grain, he gets less productive.
Maybe he has to do it on the worst
land, or he's running out of water, or something is
not going right.
Then we would change the production
possibility frontier, so that it's concave down.
Okay.
Something like that.
Do you see what I'm saying?
Diminishing returns to investment.
As you keep trying to add more and more
grain to your production, as you save more and more,
you get less and less return.
So, now we have a new
production possibility frontier that is more complicated.
So now, what happens?
Forget this straight line, which I drew first.
I'm going to draw a line, which is a curve.
And now consider a new
production possibility frontier that's curved downward.
Well, what does Robinson Crusoe do?
Well, Robinson Crusoe picks the highest
indifference curve, right, that touches this production
possibility frontier.
So, that means, he finds an
indifference curve that's tangent to it.
And he chooses that point.
Okay.
Now, okay.
Do you see it?
So, this is what Robinson Crusoe would do.
Now the interest rate is the slope
of the tangency between the indifference curve and
the production possibility frontier.
It's the same for both.
And this was the insight that von
Bawerk maybe had a little trouble getting.
There's two different things determining the interest rate.
One of them is the production possibility frontier.
And the other one is the indifference curves.
Now we have all of von Bawerk's causes.
We've got roundaboutness.
We have technical progress.
And we have impatience.
Well, the impatience would be reflected
by the slope of the indifference curves.
So, let me put it this way.
Suppose Robinson Crusoe really wanted
to consume a lot today.
He was very impatient.
That means that his indifference curves –
now, did you give me colored chalk?
We have a little yellow.
All right.
Suppose Robinson Crusoe is very impatient.
He wants to consume.
Now, he doesn't care about the future.
Then his indifference curves might look
– I'll just draw a tangency.
His indifference curves might look different.
They might look like this.
Okay?
So, he would have a tangency further to
the right, consuming more today and less in the
future.
Okay?
Now, the slope here is
different than the slope here, right?
Because I haven't changed the production possibility
frontier, but I've moved to a different point
on the production possibility frontier.
So, you can see that if Robinson Crusoe
becomes more impatient, he's going to have a tendency
to consume more.
So, if he's more impatient, his interest rate goes up.
Now, you understand that the interest rate
in the Robinson Crusoe economy is not just
about Robinson Crusoe.
It's about all – even though there's only
one person in this economy, it's about all
of the causes.
The technology is represented by the technical
progress and the roundaboutness, and the preferences
are represented by the indifference curves.
And you can see that the actual rate of
interest in his economy is determined by the tangency.
Now, on the other hand, suppose Robinson Crusoe
were very patient and really wants to live
for the future, then the highest
indifference curve that touches the production possibility
frontier might hit up here, right?
Now, that's another Robinson Crusoe.
A Robinson Crusoe with a different – with
a different – a different – a different
– a different – a different – a different –
a different – a different – a different – a
different personality, who's more patient.
Then the tangency would be up here, and
the interest rate would be much lower because
the interest rate would be the slope of
the line that goes through that tangency point,
tangent to both the indifference
curve and the production possibility frontier.
So, this is just one person in the economy.
Is this clear?
So, I've drawn a lot of lines.
Maybe I should start all over again.
We've now gotten all of Bohm-Bawerk's causes
of interest, and we've got an interest
rate.
We've tied it to production and
technology represented by the production possibility
frontier, and taste represented by the indifference curve.
But now, I want to go back to the question.
I think I've got a couple of questions.
I think I want to
add a person to the economy.
So, let me start all over again.
A second.
There's two Robinson Crusoe's, okay, in this island.
And let's start out with autonomy.
They haven't discovered each other yet.
They're on opposite sides of the island, okay?
They have the same technology, they
have the same production possibility frontier, but
they live on opposite sides of the
island, and they don't trade with each other.
So, let me start out again.
This is the same diagram, and we
have consumption today and consumption next year again.
And we have a production possibility frontier.
That's the same curve that I drew before.
And the technology is the
same for both of them, okay?
And let's suppose they have the same endowment.
But let's suppose that Crusoe A is very patient.
And Crusoe B is very patient.
Okay?
Okay.
So, Crusoe B is very impatient.
So, Crusoe A, his utility, his
indifference curves form a tangency down here.
So, this is A. And Crusoe
B's indifference curves are up here.
This is B. Okay?
And so, they are planning to plant.
That means that Crusoe A will be saving very little.
Did I say A was the
impatient one, the way I've drawn it?
Consuming a lot now and
not saving much for the future.
But it's maximizing his utility.
That's why we have the
highest indifference curve shown here,
which is tangent.
And Crusoe B is the very patient one.
And it's consuming very little
this year, and it plans to
consume a lot next year.
So, let's say they're about to plant, according to these
tastes, and then they find each other.
Now they realize there's two of us on this island.
Now we're getting a real economy with two people.
So, what should they do?
Well, the obvious thing is
that there are gains to trade.
And the kind of trade
would be in the loan market.
What they could do is, this
Crusoe B is suffering a lot of
diminishing returns to production.
So, he really shouldn't be planting so much grain,
because he's not getting much return for it.
Whereas this other guy on the
other side of the island has
very high productivity.
He can produce a lot
for a little bit of grain.
So, he should tell Crusoe, hey,
you should plant some of this
grain for me, because you
are more productive, because you're
not doing as much.
Well, in a sense, it's a
little bit of a different thing.
It's a little bit of a different thing.
In short, what will happen is,
they'll do it through a loan.
I will loan you so much grain.
There's no money.
A wants to consume a lot.
So, B will say, instead
of planting so much, we'll strike
a loan, so it will allow
you to consume along your tastes.
And what will happen in
the economy is, we'll find an
interest rate for the economy.
So, if we look at that, look
at something – I'm going to draw
a tangency.
Like, that's supposed to be a straight line.
And on this tangent line, we
have Crusoe B has maximized his
utility subject to that tangent line constraint.
And Crusoe A maximizes utility
subject to the same constraint.
And you can see that the borrowing market, as shown
over here, clears.
And when we have that kind
of equilibrium, you can see that
both A and B have
achieved higher utility than they did
when they didn't trade.
So, this is the function of a lending market.
OK?
So, A who wants to consume
a lot this period, the production
point is here.
And B lends this amount of
consumption to A, so that A
can consume a lot.
He can consume this much.
And B, since he's lent it
to A, consumes only this much
this period.
But you see, they're both better off.
They've both achieved a higher
utility than they did when they didn't trade.
They're both better off.
They're both in higher utility.
And what is the interest rate in the economy?
The interest rate is the slope of this line.
The slope of this line is
minus 1 plus the interest rate.
So, that is the Fisher theory of interest.
And now, it's much more complicated.
You can see how all of
Eugen von Baumwawach's causes play a
role.
The interest rate is not something you could have read
off from any one person's utility.
It's not just impatience.
We're both complicated people.
We both have a whole set of indifference curves.
And it's not necessarily easy
to define whether or how much,
how impatient am I. It interacts with the production
possibility frontier in a complicated way to produce a
market interest rate.
So, this is the model for
the interest of the economy that I
have developed.
And this is the model for
the interest of the economy that
Irving Fisher developed.
And so, I wanted to
just take that as a given.
Now, when you put it this
way, it all looks indisputable that
the loan market is a good thing, right?
Nothing, there's no, I can't
think of any criticism of the
two Robinson Crusoe's in going
together and forming, making a
loan.
There's nothing bad about this loan, right?
There's nothing bad about it.
And so, I'm going to do more as a result.
But I want to come back
to criticisms of lending at the
end of this lecture.
Because I, again, part of this,
I want to try to make this
course into something that talks about the purpose of
finance and the real purpose of finance.
And this story is not the
whole story about real people and how
they interact with the lending market.
But before I do that, though,
I want to do some arithmetic of
the
of finance.
Let me move on to what
I said I would talk about.
So, that's too simple for our purposes.
What I wanted to talk about
now is different kinds of loan instruments.
And the first and simplest is the discount bond.
When you make a loan to someone, you could do
it in the form of a, or between a company
or between a government and someone, a discount bond.
A discount bond pays a fixed amount at a
future date, and it sells at a discount today.
It pays no interest.
I mean, it doesn't have
annual interest or anything like that.
It merely specifies, this bond is worth so
many dollars or euros as of a future date.
And why would you buy it?
Because you pay less than that amount.
So, let's say that it's worth $100.
Okay.
So, let's say, in t periods, t years.
You know, there's some ambiguity about, I'll say t years.
And I made that a capital T, because, well.
So, what is a discount bond worth today?
Now, we have an issue of compounding, which
I want to come to in a minute.
So, let's assume, first of all, that we're
using annual compounding, and t is in years.
Okay.
Then, the price of the discount bond today, the
price today is equal to $100 all over 1
plus r to the tth point.
Okay.
So, that's the formula.
And the formula is t power, where
t is the number of years to maturity.
t years to maturity.
Okay.
And that's the formula.
In other words, 1 plus r to the tth point.
Okay.
So, 1 plus r to the tth
power is equal to 100 over p.
So, 100 over p is the ratio of my
final value to my initial investment value, if I invest
in a discount bond.
And I want to convert
that to an annual interest rate.
So, this is the formula
that allows me to do that.
So, r is also called yield to maturity.
Because the maturity is t, the
time when the discount bond matures.
So, it's as if it's paying an interest
rate, r, once per year for t years.
And we can infer.
It's a little bit complicated.
But it's a little bit complicated.
But we can infer an interest rate on it, even
though the bond itself has a price, not an interest rate.
I mean, we can calculate the
interest rate by using this formula.
Now, Fabozzi likes to emphasize.
Now, let me come back to compounding.
Maybe I'll just talk about, this is elementary, but let
me just talk about putting money in the bank here.
So, compounding.
Okay.
So, if you have annual compounding, what that means
is that, and you have an interest rate of r,
that you're, and you put your money in the
bank with annual compounding, and the interest rate is r.
That means you don't earn interest
on interest until after a year.
You put your money in today.
Half a year later, if you put in $1 today.
Half a year later, you'll have
1 plus r over $2, right?
With an interest rate r.
Three quarters of a year later, you'll
have 1 plus three quarters r dollars.
And then, a full year
later, you'll have 1 plus r.
But now, after one year, you start
earning interest on the 1 plus r.
So, a half year after that, you would have
1 plus r times 1 plus r over 2.
Okay.
And then, two years later, you'd have
1 plus r squared, and so on.
That's annual compounding.
But the bank could offer you a different formula.
They could offer you every six months.
Every six months compounding.
Twice a year compounding.
Then, here is the difference.
After half a year, you'd have
1 plus r over 2, as before.
But now, after three quarters of a year, you would have
instead, 1 plus r over 2 times 1 plus r over 4.
And so on. Okay?
Now, what Fibozzi likes to do is,
compounding every six months.
This is what might make the textbook a little confusing.
Because we naturally think of annual compounding.
A year seems like a natural interval.
But in finance, six months is more natural.
Because by convention, a lot of
bonds pay coupons every six months.
So, Fibozzi uses the letter
z to mean r over 2.
And his time as a banker, is,
you know, a little bit longer than that.
And his time intervals are six months long.
Okay?
So, that means that the formula
that Fibozzi gives for a discount bond,
since it assumes a different compounding interval,
the Fibozzi assumption, he writes,
p equals 100 all over 1
plus z to the lowercase 2 t,
where lowercase t is the number of bonds.
And lowercase t is 2 t.
And so, that's the Fibozzi formula
for the price of a discount bond.
Of course, it only applies at every six-month interval.
He's not showing what it is
at six and a half months,
or something like that.
So, that's, okay, is that clear
about compounding and about discount bonds?
Okay.
So, the fundamental concept in
finance is present discounted value.
If you have a payment coming in the future,
so, I have a payment in t years,
or 2 t, 6 months.
Okay, say semesters.
Then the present value, depending on how I compound,
the present value, well,
let's talk about annual compounding.
The present discounted value of a payment
in t years is just the amount,
which is x dollars divided by 1 plus r.
Okay?
So, x dollars divided by
1 plus r to the t.
Or if you're compounding every six months,
it would be x all over 1
plus z to the little lowercase t.
All right, lowercase t equals 2 t.
Depending, so, whenever we ask
a question about present values,
we're going to make clear what
the compounding interval we're talking about.
By the way, there's also, I
shouldn't say by the way, it's fundamental.
There's also continuous compounding.
I talked about compounding annually or twice a year.
I can do it four times a year.
I could, if I do it four times a year,
that means I pay one quarter
of the interest after three months.
And then I start earning interest on interest,
after three months, and so on.
What if you compound really often?
Not every, you could do daily compounding.
Or that would mean you would pay,
you would start earning interest
on interest 365 times a year.
The limit is continuous compounding.
Okay.
And the formula for continuous
compounding is e to the rt.
Where e is the natural number 2.718.
r is the continuously compounded interest rate.
So, your balance equals the initial amount.
What did I say?
One dollar times e to the rt.
That's continuous compounding.
Okay.
Now, if you have a number of,
the unfortunate thing is that
present values allow us to compute
present values in different ways,
depending on what kind of compounding I'm assuming.
But if I have a sequence of payments coming in,
the present discounted value of the sequence,
and suppose they come in once a year,
then it would be natural to use annual compounding.
And then the present discounted value,
pdv, is the summation of the payments.
And what am I calling them here?
x sub i, all over one plus r.
No, I say x sub t, all
over one plus r to the t.
From t equals one,
to infinity.
And that's the present discounted value
for annual compounding of annual payments.
And if, suppose the payments
are coming in every six months,
as they do with corporate bonds,
then it might be natural
to do compounding every six months.
So, then we do pdv is equal to the summation,
t equals one to infinity,
x sub t, all over one
plus r over two to the t.
And limiting, if I want to do continuous compounding,
suppose I have payments that are coming in continually,
then the present discounted value
would be the integral from zero to infinity
of x sub t, e to the minus rt dt.
So, that's the present discounted value.
And that would be a continuously compounded present value
for a continuous stream of payments.
So, if someone is offering me payments over time,
then the payments then have to be summed somehow
into a present value.
And this is,
in finance, it often happens that people are promising
to pay you something at various future intervals over time.
And you have to recognize that payments in the future
are worth less than payments today.
Just as a discount bond,
it's worth $100 in five years,
but it's not worth $100 today,
it's worth 100 all over
one plus r to the t,
appropriately compounded.
So, the interest rate,
and that's true generally,
anything in the future is worth less.
So, present discounted value is one
of the most fundamental concepts in finance.
That whenever someone is offering me
a payment stream in the future,
you discount it to the present using these formulas.
So, for example, if you are lending
to your friend to buy a house,
and the person is promising to pay you
over the years,
then you got to figure out,
well, what is that payment worth right now?
And you would take the present value of it.
There's a few present value formulas that are essential.
And I'm going to just briefly mention them.
The present value of a console
or perpetuity
is an instrument that pays
the same payment every period forever.
Okay?
It's named after the British consoles
that were issued in the 18th century.
They were British government debt
that had no expiration date.
And the British government promised
to pay you forever an amount.
Okay, what is the present value of a console?
Well, the present value of a console is,
okay, what is the present value?
Now, we'll call the amount
that the console pays its coupon.
Okay?
And let's say the coupon were one pound per year.
If it was paying one pound per year,
and we're using annual coupons,
annual compounding,
then the present discounted value
is equal to one pound, okay,
over the interest rate.
That's very simple because this bond
will always pay you one pound.
And so, what is the interest rate on it?
It's going to equal,
your one pound is equal
r over the present discounted value.
So, the price of the console should be
the payment divided by the interest rate.
Another thing that we can do,
another formula is the formula for an annuity.
Okay.
An annuity is a different kind of payment stream.
It's a console for a while, and then it stops.
An annuity pays a fixed payment each period
until the expiration of the maturity of the.
So, the formula for the,
so it pays,
let's say, x pounds.
Let's not say one pound.
If it pays x pounds every year,
then the present discounted value,
it pays x pounds from t equals one
to capital T,
and then it stops.
Capital T is the last payment.
Then the formula is x
over r times one minus one
over one plus r to the t-th power.
So, that's the constant, the annuity formula.
And that's very important,
because a lot of financial instruments are annuities.
The most important example being a home mortgage,
a traditional home mortgage.
It's a traditional home mortgage.
You might take out a 30-year
mortgage when you buy a house.
And the mortgage will generally say,
in the United States,
it's not so common in other countries,
but in the United States,
it will say,
you pay a fixed amount.
Well, usually it's monthly.
Well, let's say annually for now, okay?
A fixed amount every year as your mortgage payment.
And then you pay that
continually until 30 years has elapsed,
and then you're done.
No more payments.
Okay.
The final thing I want to
talk about is a corporate bond,
or a conventional bond,
which is a combination of
an annuity and a discount bond.
And so, a conventional corporate bond,
or government bond,
pays a coupon every six months.
So, a conventional bond
pays coupon C, an amount C,
in dollars, pounds, or whatever currency,
every six months.
And a principal plus C,
plus C at the end.
So, that means that you,
it's really an annuity and a discount bond together, right?
So, you can't just say,
well, I'm going to put a discount bond together, right?
And so,
the present discounted value for the conventional bond
would be the sum of
the present discounted value for the,
using the annuity formula for X equals C,
plus the present discounted value of the principal,
which is given by the,
well, it would be this one,
plus the income of the principal.
But now,
we have two,
because it's every six months.
And then,
I think it's the final concept
I want to get at before
talking a little bit about other matters.
I want to talk about forward rates
and the term structure of interest rates.
Now, at every point in time,
there are interest rates
of various maturities quoted.
The interest rates of various maturities quoted,
And we want to define the forward rates implicit in
those maturity formulas.
This is covered carefully in your textbook, Fibozzi.
I'm just going to do
a very simple exposition of it.
And so, the forward rates are
the concept of a forward rate,
forward interest rate, is due to Sir John Hicks.
In his 1939 book, Value and Capital.
About 20 years ago, I
was writing a chapter for the
Handbook of Monetary Economics about interest rates.
And
I was trying to confirm
who invented the concept of forward
interest rates.
So, I'll build a little story around this.
I thought it was Sir John
Hicks reading his 1939 book, and I
couldn't find any earlier reference.
So, I asked my research assistant, can you confirm for
me that the concept of
a forward interest rate is due
to Hicks?
And my graduate student looked
around and tried to find a
reference.
And he said, I don't know.
I don't know.
And he said, if you can't
find a reference, why don't you
ask Hicks?
And I said, wait a minute.
I can find a reference.
And he said, it's in the United States.
And I said, I don't know.
It's in the United States.
But he said, I don't know.
So, I found his earlier references to it.
And he could not.
And then one day, the graduate
student came to me and said,
this is like 20 years ago,
the graduate student said, why don't
you ask Hicks?
I said, wait a minute.
This book was written in 1939.
And I got no answer.
Then I got a paper
letter, they didn't have email in
those days, from Sir John Hicks.
And it was written with trembling handwriting.
And he said, my apologies
for taking so long to answer.
My health isn't good.
But he said, to answer your
question, he said, maybe I did
invent the concept of forward interest rate.
But he said, well, maybe it
was from coffee hour at the
London School of Economics, where he was
visiting in the 1920s.
Here we go.
Sir John Hicks is reminiscing
to me about what happened in
coffee time in the 1920s.
So I'm just trying to convey what he told me.
And I'm not sure if you can see it.
But he said, maybe I
did invent the concept of forward
interest rate.
Maybe it was from coffee.
But he said, maybe I
did invent the concept of forward
interest rate.
He told me they were thinking.
At any point of time, you
open the newspaper, and you see
interest rates quoted for various maturities.
That's called the term structure of interest rates.
And the term structure of interest rates, for example,
you'll find Treasury, you'll find one-year rates, there'll
be a yield on one-year bonds,
there'll be a yield on two
years, there'll be a yield quoted on three-year bonds.
And now, for most of the
world today, if you want to borrow
money for one year, it's really cheap.
In Europe, or UK, US, over
much of the world, it's like 1%.
US, it's less than 1%.
I mean, it depends on who
you are, what your borrowing rate
will be, depending on your credit history.
But if you have excellent credit, one-year interest
rates are really low.
But if you want to borrow
for 10 years, it's more like 3.5%.
So, it's higher.
And if you want to borrow
for 30 years, they might charge
you 4% or 5%.
This is the term structure of interest rates, and it's
quoted every day in the newspaper.
Well, I should say, I'm thinking 1925.
In 1925, you'd go to the newspaper to see it.
Now, you go to the internet to see it.
So, newspapers don't carry this anymore.
But I'm still in the mode
of thinking of Sir John Hook.
We're in 1925.
So, you open up the newspaper
in 1925, and you get the yield
to maturity, or the interest rate on various maturities.
All for today.
Everything that's quoted in today's paper is an interest
rate between now, today, and
so many years in the future.
The one-year interest rate quoted is the rate between now
and one year from now, right?
And the two-year interest rate
is the one year interest rate,
quoted is the rate from now to
two years from now, and so on.
So, Hicks and his coffee
hour, people were saying, well, it
seems kind of one-dimensional, because
all the rates that are
quoted are rates between now and some future date.
But what about between two future dates?
And then they thought about this at coffee hour, and
someone said, well, it's kind of unnecessary to quote them,
because they're all implicit in the term structure today.
So, that's the question.
And this is where the
concept of forward interest rate comes.
And it's explained in Fibozzi,
but I thought, I'm going to
just try to explain it in the simplest term.
Once you get the concept, it's easy.
And I'm going to assume
annual compounding to simplify things.
But in Fibozzi, being a good
financier, he does it in six
month compounding.
So, that's it.
Thank you.
So, okay.
So, now we're in, the year
is 1925, and we're in coffee hour.
And we're talking about, okay.
Suppose I expect to have, I'm
just trying to get my 100
pounds to invest in 26.
It's 25 now.
This is a whole year from the 1926.
And I want to lock in the interest rate now.
Is there any way to do that?
I mean, I could try to go
to some banker and say, can you
promise me that you'll give me
an interest rate in 1926 for
one year?
The banker might do it, but I
don't need to go to a banker
to do that.
And once I have all of
these bonds available, and if I can
both go long and short them,
then I can lock it in.
So, here's what I want to do.
This is what they were discussing at Coffey.
Buy in 1925 two-year bonds in an amount.
You've got to buy the amount right.
You've got to buy 1 plus
r sub 2, which is the two-year
yield, squared all over 1 plus r1 bonds, discount bonds.
They'll mature in two years.
OK?
And then I have to short in 1925.
I'm going to do that.
One period bond.
OK, suppose I do that.
Worth 100.
That matures at 100 pounds.
OK?
So, suppose I do that, what happens after one period?
Well, after one period, I owe 100 pounds, right?
Because I just shorted one period bond.
So, I get a 100 pound bond.
And so, I pay 100 pounds.
That's like investing 100 pounds.
At the end, I get
this amount times 100 pounds, right?
Because this is the number of bonds that I bought.
So, what is the return that I get?
The return that I get is the ratio.
Well, it gives me the,
we'll call that the forward rate
between 26 and 27, as quoted in 1925.
And so, that forward rate,
we'll say, 1 plus the forward
rate, F, is equal to 1 plus r2.
So, I get 1 plus r2
squared, all over 1 plus r1.
It's just the amount that I get.
Because I'm, see, this is, what
I'll get, if I bought this
number of bonds, I get 100
pounds times this number in two
periods in 1927.
But I put out 100 pounds in 1926.
So, the return of the amount that
I got at the end to the
amount in 27 that I put
in in 26 is given by this.
So, that's 1 plus the interest
rate I got on the bond.
So, you can compute forward rates.
I'm just showing it for a
one year ahead forward rate for a
one year loan.
But you can compute it.
So, you can compute the return
of the amount in the future
over any maturity.
And this is the formula given,
it's on page 227 of Fibozzi.
I'm not going to show you the general formula.
The expectations theory of the term structure is a theory
that, I'll write it down, expectations theory says that,
the forward rate equals the expected rate.
So, the expectation theory is
that, the expectation theory is
the expectation theory.
So, the expectation theory is that, the expectation theory
is the expected spot rate.
So, do you see what I'm saying?
Here in 1925, I opened
the London Times, and right there,
I have printed the whole term structure today.
And I can then compute using forward rate formulas, the
implied interest rates for every year in the future, even
out to 2010.
They could have computed, if they had computed, they could
have computed, if they had
bonds that were that long, I
think they had a few.
See, 1925, some bonds go out 100 years.
If you wanted to do the
one-year rate in 1925 for the
year 2011, you'd have to find
a pair of bonds, one of them
maturing in 2011, and another one maturing in 2012.
And if you did that, you
could get an interest rate for this
year.
So, that was kind of the realization.
But that Hicks got that the
whole future is laid out here
in this morning's paper.
All the interest rates for, maybe
not out to 2011, but out
to a long time in the future.
And so, what determines those interest rates?
So, Hicks, in his book,
wrote, the simplest theory is the
theory that we just, these forward rates are just
predictions of interest rates on those future dates.
So, we could go back and
see, what were they predicting for,
they weren't thinking.
So, clearly, definitively about 2011, but they must have
been, because they were trading these bonds.
And so, you could test whether the expectations theory is
rational, whether people are forming rational expectations
by looking at those forecasts and seeing, were they right?
Okay?
Now, there's a lot, there's
a huge literature on this, but
Hicks said that, I'll just stop with this.
He said that, there's a, those forecasts, the expectations
theory doesn't quite work, because there's a risk premium.
That the forward rates tend to be above the optimally
forecasted future spot rates.
Spot meaning, as quoted on that date.
Because of risk, and people
are uncertain about the future, so
they demand a higher forward
rate than they expect to see
happening in the spot rate.
So, I will stop talking technical things.
I wanted to say something.
I have so much more to say about,
but I'll have to limit due to time.
What I've laid out here
is a theory of interest rates.
And I've done some interest
rate calculations, and I've pointed
out the remarkable institutions we
have, that have, that have
interest rates for all intervals, maybe 100 years.
And so, it's all kind of,
like the whole future is planned in
these markets.
It seems impressive, doesn't it?
But the question is, is everything really, and when I
told you the Robinson Crusoe story, didn't that sound good?
Like, when the two Robinson Crusoe's discover each other,
aren't they obviously doing the right
thing to make a loan from
one to the other?
And I like that.
I think basically, everything I've said here is basically
right.
But I wanted to say that one
of the themes of this course is
about human behavior and behavioral economics.
And I wanted to talk a
little bit about borrowing and lending
and how it actually plays out in the real world.
And how our attitudes are changing, our regulatory
attitudes are changing.
So, let me just step back
and, you know, I think this
literature that Irving Fisher and Boone Bavarick and many
others who've contributed to the understanding of interest
rates is very powerful and important.
And it supersedes anything that
had been written in the last
thousands of years.
They had interest rates for thousands of years.
But that simple diagram, that Fisher diagram, came just a
short time ago.
It's hardly long ago at all.
But I wanted to step back
and think about what people said
about interest rates going way back in time.
And so, I was going to quote the Bible.
Okay.
There's a Latin.
There's a Latin word.
Do you know this word?
Do you know what that means in Latin?
Well, actually, our English word use comes from it.
So, I don't know how to pronounce it.
Usura in Latin means use.
And it means also interest.
Because what is interest?
You're giving someone the use of interest.
You're not giving them the money.
You're giving them the use of the money.
And they had other words for interest.
But this ancient word had a negative connotation.
It sounded bad.
It kind of meant something immoral.
Okay.
And so, we have a word called usury.
You know this word.
This is English now.
It's just, there's 2,000.
It goes back more than 2,000 years.
So, the Bible, I actually have it here in Latin.
I'm just curious about these things.
But I can't pronounce it right.
But it must have been written
in Greek or Aramaic or something originally.
But it uses the word usury.
Usura.
But the quotation, it says in Exodus,
If thou lent money to any of
my people that is poor by thee,
thou shalt not be to him as an usurer.
Neither shalt thou lay upon him usury.
Now, what does that mean?
Because usura can mean both interest and excessive interest.
So, it's not clear what
the Bible is saying about lending.
It sounds like it's telling
you, you can lend someone money,
but don't take any interest.
That's what it seems to be saying, but it's ambiguous.
And I was going to quote the Koran.
Now, I don't speak Arabic.
I think there's a similar ambiguity in Arabic.
So, and I'm quoting an English translation of the Koran.
Oh, you who believe, be careful of Allah
and give up the interest that is outstanding.
So, or usura.
That has been interpreted by modern Islamic
scholars as that charging interest is ungodly.
And it was interpreted by Christian scholars.
They go back and they try
to figure out what was meant.
And they couldn't figure it out either.
And times changed over the centuries.
But for thousands of years, the Catholic Church,
or maybe not thousands, I don't
know the whole history of this.
It depends on which century you're talking about.
But for many centuries,
the Catholic Church interpreted this,
as do many Muslims today.
That interest is immoral.
And therefore, the only people who
were allowed to loan were Jews.
Because they weren't subject to the, even
though it's actually the Book of Exodus.
They weren't subject to the same interpretation.
So, it was considered immoral.
And I wonder, why is that?
Why is it immoral?
Because we just saw the logic of it.
Now, this is a very interesting question.
You know, the Robinson Crusoe story, I had two
different men on the other side of the island.
And I had one of them wanting consumption
today, and one of them wanting consumption later.
Your first question is, maybe
they were wrong to be different.
Maybe they should both be doing the same thing.
Why is one of them different than the other?
The guy who's going to consume a lot today,
maybe I should have a word with this guy.
Don't do it.
You're going to be really hungry next year.
You're going to be really hungry.
And he's doing this.
So, instead of forming a loan
between the two, we should advise them.
And maybe they don't need a loan.
So, this comes back to, what
are we doing with our loans?
And are we giving people good advice?
Or do we have a tendency
in the financial world to be usurious?
Are we going after and victimizing people?
But we're not.
We haven't.
You see, it starts at something.
The way we manage our
society in the money world hurts.
So, we become willing to give
back to a foreign person money.
You know, on a vacation, it's very easy to entire醒
to me a vacation bowels, soanda having in case.
So, I wish the recognition
of the exercise in their formasm
so that it's accepted I think with every opportunity.
million websites that were encouraging you to take out a
loan to go on a vacation.
Now, is that socially conscious?
I was wondering about that.
Is it ever right to borrow
money to go on a vacation?
I mean, I've thought about that.
And then I remembered Franco
Modigliani, who is one of the
authors of your textbook, and he was my teacher.
I remember these moments from classroom, and
he was teaching us about these subjects.
And he said, he was thinking about examples of investments.
And he said, you know what?
One of the best investments I
can think of is a honeymoon.
When you get married, you go on a vacation.
Now, why are you doing that?
Is it for fun?
Probably not.
In fact, I have a
suspicion that most honeymoons are not
fun.
I think it's just people
are too uptight and tense from,
what have we just done?
And I bet, I bet that's right.
So, why do you do it?
Well, you do it as an investment, right?
You want this photograph album,
you want the memories, you're
kind of bonding.
I think he's absolutely right.
You should go on a honeymoon.
So, I did another search.
I searched on honeymoon loans.
OK?
OK.
And I got 1.7 million here.
It beat vacation loans.
So, there are many lenders ready to lend.
And you should do it.
OK?
If you're just getting married
and you don't have any money,
go to the money, the usurious
guy and ask for the honeymoon
loan.
So, I'm not sure whether it's bad.
This is the question.
I think that there are abuses.
And I wanted to just close with Elizabeth Warren.
I first met her just a few years ago.
Well, actually, I remember her book.
She wrote some important books about the reality.
She's a Harvard Law professor who wrote books.
One of her books was
published by Yale called The Fragile
Middle Class.
And it's about people who go into bankruptcy.
And she points out that in
the U.S., even back in the old
days, when the economy was good, we had a million
personal bankruptcies a year.
And she said, well, we're going
to have to do it again.
We're going to have to do it again.
And again, she said, no, let's just agree to just
go into a million personal bankruptcies a year.
This is because of borrowing.
You don't know how many bankruptcies there are
because people are ashamed when they declare bankruptcy
and they try to cover it
up from as many people as
possible.
There are as many personal bankruptcies in normal years
as there are divorces.
But you don't hear about them, right?
You hear about all kinds of divorces.
People are ashamed of divorces, too. But
they can't cover them up because everybody knows.
But they can pretty well cover
up a bankruptcy, and so they
don't talk about it.
So what Elizabeth Warren is saying, she thinks that the
lending industry is victimizing people.
It's advertising for vacation loans and the like.
And then they don't tell people about the bad things
that will come.
So she wrote an article, and
this is interesting, it was in
Harvard Magazine.
And that's a magazine that
I suspect none of you read.
Anyone read Harvard Magazine?
OK.
It's the Harvard Alumni Magazine.
It goes out to all graduates of Harvard.
So you don't read it, and
you probably will never read it.
You will be a reader
of the Yale Alumni Magazine, which
will start arriving in your doorstep after you graduate.
And it will also include
your obituary in the next century
when that comes.
But the Harvard Alumni Magazine published this
wonderful article by Elizabeth describing all of the abuses
that happened in lending in the United States.
And I think it's an unbelievable.
I don't know how I ended up reading it.
I think it was just such
a nicely written piece, that it
just became one of their success stories.
Most people don't read that magazine, but I read it.
And a lot of people read it.
And she was so successful in convincing the public.
This is just two years ago.
Two years.
Three years ago.
She was so successful that she got a Consumer Financial
Protection Bureau inserted into the Dodd-Frank bill.
And we now have a
regulator, a new regulator, that's supposed
to stomp on these usurious practices.
So it's kind of an inspirational story.
But the downside of it
is, she got too carried away
criticizing the lending industry in that,
and she didn't know it
was going to be a problem.
And she doesn't know it
And she didn't know it
was going to be a problem.
She didn't know it was going to be a problem.
And she didn't know it
was going to be a problem.
I mean, she held her
head up high on the wall.
I think she said, well, I
don't know, I don't know, but
I don't know, but I don't know.
She's got a nice article.
It makes them sound worse than they really are.
And so, Obama could not
appoint her to head the Consumer
Financial Protection Bureau, because it would be too
politically controversial.
So she is now the person
trying to find someone to head her
bureau.
But I think that this
is just another step, and it's
happening in Europe and other places.
Europe and other places, the financial crisis has made us
more aware of bad financial practices.
And so usury is again on our mind.
Usury is abusive lending that's taken without concern
for the person who's borrowing.
And I think that what it means
to me is that we'll come back
to talk about regulation in another lecture.
But that the original Irving Fisher story and Boehm-Bawerk
story about interest was right.
And even vacation loans, especially honeymoon loans,
are right.
But we need government regulation to prevent abuses.
And we do still have abuses in the lending process.
So I'll stop with that,
and I'll see you on Monday.